Hey, what's up guys? My name is Cherno.
Welcome back to my C++ series. So, today
we're going to be talking all about
iterators. This is going to serve as
more of an introductory video to
iterators. A lot of people have been
asking me, what are iterators? Should I
be using iterators? Have they been
somewhat replaced in the language? This
especially comes up a lot in
universities who are still maybe not
using the latest C++ standard. In fact,
a lot of people message me and say, help
me, my university is using C++ 03. Which
is a shame because it's 2020, but we're
not going to get into the educational
system in this video. The point is, what
are iterators and do I really need to
know how to use them? So, iterators are
essentially a way for you to iterate
over a collection of elements. Now, the
thing is, an iterator is really up to
the implementation in terms of how it's
used, meaning that I could write a class
called Apple and then add an iterator to
it.
That might not make sense to you, but I
could use it in some kind of special
way. It's kind of like operator
overloading. You can make the plus plus
operator do anything. But, for the most
case, if we look at the standard C++
library, we can see that iterators are
usually used for iterating over data
structures. So, whether that be a simple
array that you want to traverse or get
through every element in that array.
Maybe you have a vector, you want to go
backwards through every element. Maybe
you have something a little bit more
complicated like a set or a map or even
a tree data structure. I want to
traverse that. How do I do that? Well,
you need to use an iterator. It's really
easy to overlook iterators when you're
just dealing with a simple data
structure like a vector because we can
simply use the index operator. Using the
square brackets, we can simply stick a
value into there and retrieve that
element at that given index. But, this
doesn't always work for other data
structures such as sets which don't
really contain all of our elements in
order. So, anyway, long story short
because I honestly think this does not
need to be complicated at all. Iterators
are used to iterate over a collection of
elements, and iterating over them is
really simple, as we'll see in a minute.
But first, you know what isn't stuck in
2003 in terms of education? Skillshare.
For those of you who do not know what
Skillshare is, Skillshare is an online
learning platform, a community of people
who come together to learn a new skill
on the internet. Whatever it is that
you're trying to learn, whether that be
illustration, photography, marketing,
business, productivity,
literally almost anything. Skillshare
has thousands of amazing classes for you
to choose from, and I love the fact that
they're all really concise and simple
and to the point. Even if you don't need
to learn a new skill, I mean, I didn't
think that I wanted to learn about
illustration, but to be honest, it's
been helping me relax so much, which I
feel is really needed these days.
Something like productivity, it it's not
something that you necessarily always
set out to learn, but if you if you come
across a class that teaches you to be
more productive,
why not spend a few minutes going
through that? And you can do that with
Skillshare because of those concise
classes. Coming in at just under $10 a
month for an annual subscription, it is
an amazing offer, but an even better
offer is the fact that Skillshare is
offering the first 1,000 people who
click the link in the description below
and sign up two free months of
Skillshare Premium. That's two whole
months to check out the wide variety of
courses that they have on that platform
and decide for yourself if you want to
stay and learn more or not. Huge thank
you, as always, to Skillshare for
sponsoring this video. Let's dive in and
take a look at what iterators are all
about. So, as mentioned earlier,
iterators are used to iterate over a
collection of data. Now, you can really
interpret this however you like. It's
possible to write custom iterators to do
a whole range of things, but usually
when we think of an iterator, we think
of having a collection of values, such
as this vector here, and we want to
traverse the entire collection, part of
the collection, maybe we want to go
backwards through the collection. We
essentially have the desire to get
through at least some of the values
inside this collection. So, how do we do
that? Well, let's look at some simple
examples. We have a vector here. We have
five values. How do I print them all out
to the console? There are a number of
ways we could of course do that. The
most common way which you'll probably
think of is a for loop that simply
iterates through values.size like this
so that we go through all of the five
values that we have here. And then we
simply use the index operator here with
the I variable to just retrieve the data
at a particular index inside our array
here. So, if I print this out into the
console like this,
and I'll add in a little std::cin.get
over here, we should see 1 2 3 4 5 being
printed out to the console. And you can
see that's what we get. So, we've
essentially iterated through this entire
collection. And this is a pretty common
way of doing that. Now, let's also look
at another way that we might do this
because we don't really need this I
variable. Is there a cleaner way that we
can write this? And of course, there's
something called a range-based for loop
since C++ 11. So, what we can actually
do is write the data type here, which is
int, a name for the current element that
we're iterating over, and then finally
the actual collection, which in this
case is values. So, in other words,
we're going through all of the values
here. And then we now have this integer
value to play with. That's our current
value's I equivalent. So, we can just
simply print that out to the console
like this. And well, you can see that
that that results in some very very
clean code. This is usually my preferred
way of iterating through collections if
I don't need that I variable. And there
you can see we have the same result as
before.
So, how does this even work? I mean, it
looks like seemingly magic code, and it
seems to work for this vector class. So,
what exactly makes it work with the
vector class? Does the vector class
contain something specific that makes
this range-based for loop work? And how
does that work? So, the answer is yes,
it has something called an iterator.
Now, we're not really going to get into
this too much. There's a lot of
different types of iterators here, and
we're actually going to even have a look
at writing our own iterators for our
custom data structure classes in the
future. But today, we're just going to
discuss how it actually works in
practice and how you can use it.
Basically, a range-based for loop works
because the vector class provides a
begin and end function, which returns an
iterator at a particular position. So,
in other words, this is really just some
shorthand code for the more extended
version, which we're going to take a
look at here. So, if we were to write
this out, you'll see that std::vector
with that template specialization of int
actually has another type inside it
called iterator. And there's a few
different ones, as you can probably see
here. There's iterator, there's reverse
iterator, there's const iterator. So,
just the regular iterator is what we can
use to iterate through the values in a
forward fashion in forward direction
from beginning to end. Reverse iterator
will do the opposite. It will actually
start at the end and go back to the
beginning. And then, the const versions
of these are the same, but we can use it
on a const vector because it's not going
to actually let us affect the values.
It's not going to let us mutate the
values, just simply read them. So, if we
just select the normal iterator, that's
what we have here, how can we use this
to iterate through all of the variables
or all of the elements inside this
std::vector? Well, you'd write a for
loop just like you did here. So, we'd
have an iterator, we can call it IT.
That's a common name for it, for
iterator. And we'll set this to the
beginning of our collection, which is
going to be values.begin.
Then, we need to check the end
conditions. So, in other words, just
like with any other for loop, at what
condition does this for loop break? At
what condition does it terminate? So, it
terminates if this iterator, or rather,
at what condition does it not terminate,
right? So, this for loop will run as
long as this statement is going to be
true. So, as long as the iterator is not
equal to the end of this collection. So,
values.end will return an iterator that
is actually already outside of the
accepted range. It's basically an
invalid iterator. So, this is not really
the end. It's not the last element. It's
the element after the last element, if
that makes sense. And then finally, we
need to write iterator plus plus. You
can also write it as plus plus iterator
or as a postfix as well, iterator plus
plus. It doesn't matter in this case.
Now, let me just slightly clean up this
code and drop it down a bit so that you
can see it all. Okay. So, that's it.
We're going through all of our values.
So, now that we have an iterator though,
how do we get the value at that iterator
position? Well, you have to dereference
the iterator as if it was a pointer.
This works because they've just
implemented this dereference operator
kind of asterisk function inside the
actual iterator class. Okay. So, now to
print this out to the console, we'll
follow the same strategy as before. We
simply dereference the iterator and
print it out like this. And now what we
should see is our 1 2 3 4 5 elements
being printed for the third time. And
that is of course what we see over here.
Great. So, why would you ever use
iterators like this? And to be honest,
the answer is you probably wouldn't
these days because a range-based for
loop is essentially shorthand for this.
And of course, it looks a lot cleaner.
However, there are certain situations
where you might want to manipulate the
position of the iterator. A good example
is if you want to erase an element but
still keep iterating over the rest of
the collection. In that case, the
iterator gets invalidated. You have to
deal with that. Or maybe you want to
insert something into the middle based
on a certain condition. There's a few
different scenarios in which you just
simply can't use this because it just
wouldn't work. You need to be able to
manipulate the position of the iterator.
And we'll probably get into those in a
future video. But obviously, for
something like a vector or an array with
an index operator that simply takes in a
numerical index, it just the same as
like it would for an array here, they're
not really necessary. You don't actually
have to write code like this because we
can, of course, just write a normal for
loop and use I as the index. However,
iterators are essentially mandatory for
other types that don't have such a
simple indexing system because, of
course, not everything is just a
contiguous array with an index like we
have here. I mean, think of something
like a tree data structure. How do we
traverse through a tree? We can't just
increment an index. What about an
unordered set? I mean, that contains a
bunch of unordered elements. If I wanted
to print all of them out to the console,
how would I do that? The example I'm
going to show you is specifically the
unordered map here. So, an unordered map
is essentially a hash map. It obviously
doesn't store its variables in any kind
of order, and we need to actually know
the keys of the entries if we want to
get the values out of there unless we
iterate through them, and that's what
we're going to do here. So, let's create
a little map here. I'm going to just
write an unordered map
of STD string to maybe int. We'll call
this map. So, maybe this will like
contain like some kind of name like
Cherno and maybe an associated score.
So, we'll write Cherno 5 and maybe, I
don't know, C++ 2 because obviously I'm
cooler than C++. So, with this map in
mind, if I wanted to iterate through it,
how would I do it? Well, obviously I
can't use a for loop like this because
if I did that, well, my index would just
be like zero or one if I checked the map
size, and that's not what I need. I need
to actually iterate using the correct
keys here. So, I'm forced to write some
sort of iterator. So, let's write this
out as a for loop that actually uses
iterators. So, what I'll do is I'll take
the entire type, and you can see it's
getting quite long, and then maybe I
don't want to like modify these values.
I just want to access them, so I want to
use a const iterator. Okay, this is a
huge type, and because of that, it's
pretty common to use either a type def
or using along with the type. So, in
other words, maybe I could replace this
part of it if I wanted to and just call
it a score map, and then that would
obviously simplify things a lot, so I
can just do this now. Maybe I even want
to define some kind of score map const
iterator or something like that. I could
also do that by just assigning this to
score map const iterator, and now all I
have to do is write code like this. I
honestly end up doing stuff like this a
lot. I don't I don't ever really use
using with iterators like this, but I do
use it with the type sometimes, so I'll
leave it like that here, and then just
implement this as score map const
iterator. So, iterating through this
map, I'll set the iterator equal to the
beginning of the map, of course, like I
did before. I'll make sure that it
iterates until we reach the end of the
map, and then I'll increment the
iterator. Now, this is a little bit
different because this is a map. I'm
iterating through a map, so how does
that work? I don't just have one
element, right? Like I would with like a
set or a vector or an array or something
like that. I actually have two elements,
the key and the value, so how do I
access them? Well, instead of just
dereferencing it, you can actually use
the arrow operator and access two little
elements here. We have first and second.
First is going to be the key, so I can
just go ahead and assign that to key
like that. And then the second one is
going to be my value, and I'll just use
the ampersand here to get this as a
reference so that I'm not actually
copying the value. So, I have iterator
first and iterator second. Let's go
ahead and print that out to the console.
We'll print the key followed by an equal
sign and then value like this. Let's go
ahead and run this, and in fact, what I
might do is just take away the other
code that we had here to keep our
console nice and clean. All right, check
this out. So, we have channel equals
five and C++ equals two. Cool, we're
able to iterate through all of this.
Now, how can we maybe improve this code
to make it a little bit better? How can
we use the same kind of range-based for
loops, but with a map? Well, let's check
that out. So, I'm going to write for
auto KV, that's going to stand for key
value in this case, and then map. Yeah,
it's that simple. So, what this will do
is actually retrieve this pair, this
iterator first and iterator second. If
you actually look at what it is, it's an
STD pair. So, this is us now retrieving
that STD pair, and now we can actually
access the elements from within that.
So, I still need this, unfortunately,
but this obviously cleans up the code
because I can just do KV.first
and KV.second like that. And then
obviously, if I print this out, I should
get the same result. Let me just add
some end lines between this and here,
maybe. Let's see what we get. All right,
as you can see, we get the same result,
obviously, but this again looks a lot
cleaner. Now, can we do better than
that? Well, yes, we can. As of C++ 17,
we're able to use structured bindings.
What that means is that this code is
going to look even cleaner. We can
actually retrieve this key and value
right here inside this statement. We can
simply write auto key, value with these
kind of square brackets here, and
iterate through our map. So, if I drop
this over here,
that's all we end up with. And if I hit
a five, there we go. We're now iterating
through this map three different ways.
And of course, this code looks much,
much cleaner. Now, keep in mind that you
will have to make sure that your
compiler supports C++ 17 and that you're
actually compiling with that. If we go
into properties here as an example, you
can see that my C++ language standard
under C++ and language in Visual Studio
is set as C++ 17. If you're getting
compiler errors, which is quite common,
then make sure that you're actually
compiling with C++ 17. Okay, so in
summary, the only way that we can
iterate through a map or a set or
something that is essentially unordered
and doesn't have a simple kind of
incrementing index system is by using an
iterator. And today, we've discussed
both using a normal iterator, a const
iterator, range-based for loops, which
actually use iterators, as well as
structured bindings with maps, which is
pretty cool. And just to be super clear,
the reason these range-based for loop
shortcuts work is because we have an
actual begin function inside our map or
inside our well, whatever collection or
data structure we're using that actually
returns an iterator in the first place.
If we didn't have that, then that would
in fact not work. Okay, so hopefully
that was a good introduction to
iterators. There is of course a lot more
topics that we can actually cover in
terms of iterators. I would like to for
one write our own iterators and we'll be
adding them to the data structures that
we've been going over the last few
episodes of this series as well. As I
mentioned, there's also some advanced
things that you can try to do with
iterators and I would encourage you to
try that out as an exercise, as
homework, if you will. So for example,
try and remove an element from the
center of a vector and see if you can
adjust the iterator to deal with that.
And likewise, maybe add an element into
the middle of the vector and see if your
iterator can deal with that. Those are
great exercises and I might be revealing
those solutions in the future. But
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this
video. If you did, as always, please do
not forget to hit that like button and
subscribe if you are new to this
channel. We've got plenty more C++
videos coming soon. Next time, I think
we'll have a go at actually writing our
own iterators and adding them to our
data structure classes. But until then,
I hope you guys have a great day.
Definitely don't forget to check out
Skillshare using the link in the
description below and I will see you
next time. Goodbye.